Guide to the Arnold Gesell and Colleagues Publications Collection
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
Arnold Gesell and Colleagues Publications collection
1922-1991
1930-1959
Ms Coll 41
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
2.5
(5 boxes)
Arnold Gesell was head of the Psycho-Clinic and later of the Clinic of Child Development at the Yale School of Medicine from 1911 to 1948. Some of his former collaborators founded the Gesell Institute for Child Development in 1950 in New Haven to carry on his work. The collection contains non-book publications by Arnold Gesell and his collaborators as well as of some of the staff members of the Gesell Institute. Publications include not only reprints of professional articles, but also popular articles from newspapers, magazines, and newsletters of organizations; radio broadcasts; book reviews by Gesell; clippings of reviews of Gesell's books; and testimony for legislation. There are also some typescripts, possibly unpublished, and a small amount of manuscript material related to publications.
no content
Gesell, Arnold, 1880-1961
Gesell Institute of Child Development
Yale University. Clinic of Child Development
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by the Child Study Center, 2012.
Custodial History
These materials were maintained by Louise Bates Ames, initially for Arnold Gesell and the Clinic of Child Development. The files may have been brought to the Gesell Institute of Child Development, since Ames continued to add materials and Arnold Gesell borrowed some of them after 1950.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Arnold Lucius Gesell, psychologist, pediatrician, and expert on infant and child development, was born in Alma, Wisconsin on June 21, 1880. He obtained a B. Phil. from the University of Wisconsin in 1903, a Ph.D. in psychology from Clark University in 1906, and an M.D. from Yale in 1915. From 1911 to 1930, he was Director of the Psycho-Clinic, associated with the Department of Pediatrics and the New Haven Dispensary. From 1930 to his retirement in 1948, he was Director Clinic of Child Development, which was initially part of the Institute of Human Relations. In 1948, Gesell's Clinic was closed and the staff dispersed. In its place, the Child Study Center was established under Milton Senn. Gesell remained a Research Associate in Child Vision at the Child Study Center from 1948 to 1950. Gesell was a pioneer in proposing detailed norms for the development of infants and children. He was also one of the earliest investigators to use motion pictures to capture infant and child behavior for research and education. Children were studied and filmed in within a dome-like structure, where researchers could view them from the outside. Several films were made for a wider audience and distributed through Encyclopedia Brittanica Films. Gesell also created a number of instruments, tests, and scales for examining children. He was the first author of many books co-authored by staff members of the Clinic of Child Development, among them The First Five Years of Life: The Preschool Years (1940), Developmental Diagnosis: Normal and Abnormal Child Development (1941), Infant and Child in the Culture of Today (1943), and The Child from Five to Ten (1946). Many of his articles and some of his books were directed to parents and the general public. In 1950, Frances Ilg, M.D., Louise Bates Ames, Ph.D., and Janet Learned, colleagues and co-authors of Gesell, created the Gesell Institute of Child Development, in New Haven, where they and colleagues published books, research papers, and articles for the public; provided developmental tests; and offered the services of a clinic. Early research at the Gesell Institute focused on the child from ten to sixteen, and on vision. Gesell was associated with the Institute until his death on May 29, 1961 in New Haven.
Scope and Contents
Series 1 includes a broad range of publications of Arnold Gesell from 1937 to 1956. They include not only reprints of professional articles, but also popular articles from newspapers, magazines, and newsletters of organizations; popular pamphlets; radio broadcasts; unpublished talks, book reviews by Gesell; clippings of reviews of Gesell's books; and testimony for legislation. There are also some typescripts, possibly unpublished, and a small amount of correspondence and manuscript material related to publications. Series 2 includes publications, typescripts, and published dissertations of Gesell's students and colleagues at the Clinic of Child Development and the Gesell Institute. This series is much more incomplete than Series 1. These files appear to have been maintained by Louise Bates Ames, Gesell's assistant at the Yale Clinic of Child Development from 1933 to 1948. She received a Ph.D. under Gesell in 1936 and was later one of the founders of the Gesell Institute of Child Development.
Arrangement
Organized in two series: 1. Publications of Arnold Gesell. 2. Publications of Colleagues and Students. Series 1 is arranged according to the system of the Gesell Institute (see below), roughly chronological. Series 2 is arranged alphabetically by person.
Child development; Cinematography; Infants; Infants -- Development; Pediatricians; Psychologists; Child psychology; Amatruda, Catherine Strunk, 1903-; Ames, Louise Bates, 1908-; Castner, Burton Menaugh, 1898-; Gesell, Arnold, 1880-1961; Halverson, Henry Marc, 1884-; Franzen-Hellersberg, L., 1893-; Ilg, Frances L. (Frances Lillian), 1902-1981; Rodell, Janet Learned; Thompson, Helen, 1897-
- Publications of Arnold Gesell, 1937-1959; 1.
  Arrangement
  Arranged according to the system used by the Yale Clinic of Child Development and the Gesell Institute. Numbers are sequential (some are missing). A number preceded by an A is an article, a number preceded by a B is a book, and a number preceded by Br is a book review. The earliest number in the collection is 211, published in 1937. See folder 1 for information on earlier numbers.
  - "List of Reprints Filed in Transfer File", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Lists titles (not journals or dates) of publications numbered A-2 to A-205 and how many copies had been saved. Another page lists full citations of reprints for which there were no copies. A-1 was dated 1898.
  - A-211 - A-214, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - B-215 Reviews of The Psychology of Early Growth (1938) (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Arnold Gesell, Helen Thompson, and Catherine Strunk, The Psychology of Early Growth, including Norms of Infant Behavior and a Method of Genetic Analysis (New York: Macmillan Co., 1938).
  - A-216 - A-219, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - A-220 - A-227, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - B-230 Reviews of Biographies of Child Development (1939) (Box 7, Folder 6)
    Arnold Gesell, Burton M. Castner, Helen Thompson, and Catherine S. Amatruda, Biographies of Child Development: The Mental Growth Careers of Eighty-Four Infants and Children. A Ten Year Study from the Clinic of Child Development at Yale University (New York: Paul B. Hoeber, 1939).
  - A-231 - A-239, 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - A-240 - A-246, 1938-1940 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - B-247 Staff Conferences on The First Five Years of Life (1940), 1939 January 24 -1939 May 15 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Typed detailed minutes of staff meetings about aspects of this book. AG=Arnold Gesell, BMC= Burton M. Castner, CSA=Catherine Strunk Armatruda, EM=Edith Meyer, FLI=Frances Lillian Ing, JL=Janet Learned, HMH=Henry Marc Halverson, and HT=Helen Thomas.
  - B-247 Reviews of The First Five Years of Life (1940), 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Arnold Gesell, Henry M. Halvorsen, Helen Thompson, Frances L. Ilg, Burton M. Castner, Louise Bates Ames, and Catherine S. Amatruda, The First Five Years of Life: The Preschool Years (New York; Harper & Brothers, 1940).
  - B-247a - B-247c Publications related to The First Five Years of Life (1940) (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Popular article, pamphlet, and radio talk based on The First Five Years of Life.
  - A-248 - A-249, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Gesell correspondence on the World's Fair Exhibit, 1940 June (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Correspondence with Mr. A. Terhune, Eastman Kodak, and others concerning materials "for three key photographic assemblies representative of the applications of cinematography in the scientific study of Child Development."
  - A-250 - A-259, 1940-1941 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Includes copies of B-257: [Arnold Gesell], Booklet of General Instructions to accompany the Gesell Developmental Schedules (New York: The Psychological Corporation, 1940),
  - A-260 - A-267, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Includes a radio talk for the National Congress of Parents and Teachers.
  - B-263 Reviews of Wolf Child and Human Child (1941) (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Arnold Gesell, Wolf Child and Human Child: Being a Narrative Interpretation of the Life History of Kamala, the Wolf Girl, Based on the Diary Account of a Child who was Reared by a Wolf and WhoThen Lived for Nine Years in the Orphanage of Midnapore, in the Province of Bengal, India (New York: Harper & Brothers, [1941]).
  - B-266 Memoranda related to illustrating Developmental Diagnosis (1941), 1940 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - B-266 Reviews of Developmental Diagnosis: Normal and Abnormal Child Development (1941) (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Arnold Gesell and Catherine S. Amatruda, Developmental Diagnosis: Normal and Abnormal Child Development, Clinical Methods and Practical Application s (New York: Paul B. Hoeber, Inc., 1941).
  - A-270 - A-279, 1941-1944 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - B-280 Reviews of Infant and Child in the Culture of Today (1943), 1943-1944 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Arnold Gesell and Frances Ilg, in collaboration with Louise B. Ames and Janet Learned, Infant and Child in the Culture of Today: The Guidance of Development in Home and Nursery Schoo l (New York: Harper & Row, 1943).
  - B-280 More reviews of Infant and Child in the Culture of Today, 1943-1944 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Br-282 - A-288, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Includes mimeograph publication, Child Adoptions in Connecticut (New Haven: Child Welfare Asociation, 1943), a pamphlet on whether Connecticut women should engage in war work, and copies of notes on "Creative Behavior and Giftedness in Child and Adult."
  - A-290 - A-298, 1943-1944 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Includes a mimeograph of a radio talk distributed by Yale University News Bureau: Arnold Gesell, "War Conditions Increase the Need for Child Guidance," October 24, 1943.
  - A-300 - A-303, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Includes a mimeographed statement made at two conferences on employed mothers, "Individual Versus Group Care of Infants."
  - B-304 Reviews of The Embryology of Behavior (1945) (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Arnold Gesell in collaboration with Catherine S. Amatruda, The Embryology of Behavior: The Beginnings of the Human Mind (New York: Harper & Brothers, 1945).
  - A-332 - A-337, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Reprints from A-305 to A-331 were not part of the collection.
  - A-347 - A-349, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Includes Arnold Gesell and Louise Bates Ames, Guide to the Yale Films of Child Development (Chicago: Encyclopedia Brittanica Films, 1945), and "Dr. Gesell of Yale tells why Senate Bill 117, eliminating compulsory investigation prior to adoption should not pass," published in an mimeographed issue of Under the Golden Dome by the Connecticut Child Welfare Associaton.
  - A-350 - A-359, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - A-361 - A-369, 1947-1949 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - A-370 - A-379, 1947-1949 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Includes correspondence with Jarvis M. Morse, Director, Education Section, U.S. Savings Bonds Division; a typescript of Gesell's article, "The Psychology of the Money Sense."; and a typescript of the "The Clinical Diagnosis and Supervision of Infant Development," the Alpha Kappa Kappa Lectureship.
  - A-380 - A-389, 1949-1950 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Includes correspondence and a typescript concerning the publication of "The Development of Child Vision" in Scientific American, and at the request of the U.S. State Department, in a magazine, Neue Auslese, published jointly by the American and British Governments for distribution in Germany and Austria. This folder also contains a review of Arnold Gesell, Frances L. Ilg, and Glenna E. Bullis, Vision: Its Development in Infant and Child (New York: Paul B. Hoeber, 1949).
  - A-390 - A-399, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    Includes an English translation of the preface to the Italian translation of The First Five Years of Life.
  - A-401 -A-403, A-407, 1951-1952 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    Includes the Brotherhood Week Newspaper Kit(1952) by the National Conference of Christians and Jews, which focuses on donating blood for the Korean War. In the kit is a typescript by Gesell, "Brotherhood Begins at Home."
  - A-411 - A-419, 1952-1954 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    Includes a typescript translation of the preface for the Japanese edition of The First Five Years of Life.
  - A-420 - A-426, 1953-1959 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    Gesell's last publication was an introduction to Louis A. Warren, Lincoln's Youth: Indiana Years, Seven to Twenty-one, 1816-1830 (Indianapolis: Indiana Histoircal Society, 1959).
  - Miscellaneous, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 14)
    Gesell's commentary for an unidentified document on the history of "mental deficiency. " The comments contain biographical information and information on responses to "mental deficiency" in Connecticut and particularly, New Haven.
- Publications of Colleagues and Students, 1922-1994; 2.
  This series contains publications by colleagues and students of Arnold Gesell at the Yale Clinic of Child Development and the Gesell Institute. It includes several published dissertations by students working at the Clinic, and also papers by staff at the Gesell Institute after the death of Gesell in 1961. Some of the items were published in popular magazines and newspapers. The arrangement retains that of Louise Bates Ames, that is, alphabetically by first author.
  - Amatruda, Catherine Strunk, 1942, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    Catherine Amatruda received an M.D. from Cornell in 1926. She served as a Research Associate and Assistant Professor in Child Deveopment from 1930 to 1948. She was an Assistant Professor of Pediatrics from 1948 to her death in 1949. Amatruda was Gesell's main collaborator.
  - Apell, Richard J., 1951, 1955, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    Richard J. Apell, Doctor of Optometry, worked with Gesell at Yale on the Child Vision Research Project, and was associated with the Gesell Institute since its founding in 1950. In 1979, he was serving as Associate Director of the Gesell Institute.
  - Bowen, Elisabeth, 1978 and n.d. (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Castner, Burton Menaugh, 1929-1935 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    Burton M. Caster received his Ph.D. from Yale in 1931 and was associated with the Psycho-Clinic and Yale Clinic of Child Development as a Research Assistant and Clinical Examiner from 1925 to 1940.
  - Cobb, Margaret Evertson, 1922 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Cockrell, Dura Louise, 1930, 1935 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Chase, Joan Ames, 1965-1972 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Gesell, Beatrice Chandler, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    Beatrice Chandler Gesell was the wife of Arnold Gesell and co-author of T he Normal Child and Primary Education (1912).
  - Goodenough, Evelyn Wiltshire, 1957-1967 and n.d. (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Evelyn Goodenough received an M.A. from Yale in 1939. See also Evelyn Goodenough Pitcher.
  - Gridley, Pearl Farwell, 1933 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Halverson, Henry M., 1922-1932 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    Henry Marc Halverson received his Ph.D. from Clartk University in 1922. He was a Research Associate at Yale, with a specialty in photography of child behavior, from 1926 to 1942.
  - Halverson, Henry M., 1933-1938 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    Includes a typescript discussion at a meeting on January 21, 1938 at the Clinic of Child Development on Halverson's research on the sucking responses of infants.
  - Halverson, Henry M., 1940-1944 and n.d. (Box 4, Folder 8)
    Includes original data (n.d.) on "An experimental study of prehension by means of systematic cinema records of cube behavior."
  - Hellersberg, Elisabeth F., 1954, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - "Hellersberg Test", 1961 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    Mimeograph of Elisabeth Hellersberg, "The Horn-Hellersberg Test: A Personality Test Used for Testing the Individual's Relation to Reality," and separate test blanks. First copyrighted in 1945.
  - Hillgard, Josephine Rohrs, 1932, 1933 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    Hillgard received a Ph.D. from Yale in 1933.
  - Hiscock, Ira V., 1920s (Box 4, Folder 12)
    Typescript: "A Study of Norms for Growth amd Nutrition on the Pre-School Child." Hiscock was a member of the Department of Public Health at Yale School of Medicine.
  - Huang, I., 1943-1945 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Ilg, Frances L., 1944, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    Frances Ilg, a pediatrician, received her M.D. from Cornell University in 1929. She was associated with the Clinic of Child Development from 1932 to 1950. She attained the rank of Assistant Professor of Child Development from 1937 to 1947. Ilg was a co-author of several of Gesell's books.
  - Ilg, Frances L., 1953-1972 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    Includes reprint of Frances L. Ilg, "The Gesell Institute of Child Development," Connecticut State Medical Journal, 17 (1953): 215-216.
  - Ilg, Frances L. -- Typescript talks and papers, 1961 and n.d. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Keliher, Alice V., 1929, 1932, and n.d. (Box 5, Folder 2)
    Includes a typescript report, "The Use of the Cinema in Education."
  - Ling, Bing-Chung, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Liu, Phyllis, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Lord, Elizabeth, 1930 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    Elizabeth Lord received her Ph.D. from Yale in 1929.
  - Marquis, Dorothy Postle, 1933 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - McElwain, Pauline, 1937 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - McGinnis, John M., 1930 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    John M. McGinnis received his Ph.D. from Yale in 1929.
  - Metraux, Ruth W., 1944-1965 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    Ruth Metraux, who received a Ph.D. from the University of Michigan in 1941, was a Research Associate in Child Development from 1942 to 1948.
  - Meyer, Edith, ca. 1939 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    Edith Meyer obtained a D.Phil. in Leipzig in 1933. She was a Sterling Fellow in Psychology, 1938-1939, and a Research Assistant from 1940 to 1944. The folder contains typescripts, especially "Comprehension of Spatial Relations in Pre-School Children."
  - Meyer, Edith, 1938 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    Typescripts on perceptual and orientational behavior in conjunction with the First Five Years of Life project. "Not used"
  - New Haven Rickets Study, 1920s-1930s (Box 5, Folder 12)
    Typescript: "The Psycho-Developmental Consequences of Rickets (A Preliminary Summary and Report)." No author or date is given. The Rickets Study was carried out by the Department of Pediatrics.
  - Oak, Lura (Sawyer), 1930 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    "Digest" of her 1930 Yale Ph.D. dissertation, "Motor Difficulties of Left-Handed Children in Learning to Write and Draw."
  - Padula, William V., 1978-1979 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    William Padula, O.D., was Director of Vision Research at the Gesell Institute of Child Development. See also Apell, Richard J. (Box 3, folder 16).
  - Pasamanick, Benjamin, 1946-1966 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    Benjamin Pasamanick was a psychiatrist and educator. Several of his articles were co-authored with his wife, Dr. Hilda Knobloch.
  - Pitcher, Evelyn Goodenough, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    See also Goodenough, Evelyn Wiltshire (Box 4, folder 4).
  - Richardson, Helen M., 1934 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    Helen Richardson received her Ph.D. from Yale in 1931.
  - Steinau, Barbara Hill, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Strayer, Lois Curry, 1930 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    Lois Curry Strayer was a graduate student at Yale in 1929 but did not graduate.
  - Streff, John, 1972, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    Includes a typescript copy of John W. Streff, O.D. and Richard N. Walker, Ph.D., "Notes on a Perceptual Program for Schools: A Problem-Solving Approach," Gesell Institute of Child Development, 1972.
  - Swan (Coleman), Carla, 1938 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    This item is her published Yale Ph.D. dissertation working under Arnold Gesell.
  - Thompson, Helen, 1929-1964 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    Helen Thompson received her Ph.D. from Columbia University and served as a Research Associate in the Psycho-Clinic and the Clinic of Child Deveopment from 1926 to 1941. Her specialty was biometry and statistics. She was a co-author of several of Gesell's books. Later she was associated with the Gesell Institute.
  - Washburn, Ruth Wendell, 1929, 1933 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    The 1929 item is a publication of part of her 1929 Ph.D. dissertation under Arnold Gesell at the Yale Psycho-Clinic.